Chinese fans gave it love,
North American viewers panned it hard;
critics praised it while roasting it,
most said it was decent but just lacked that spark.
Why has 'Zootopia 2' drawn such polarized audience reviews?
because 'Zootopia' is a film about America,
and today's U.S.
is no longer the one that moves us so easily —
hello, I'm backlash
I saw 'Zootopia 2' the other day,
of course in the original version.
While its script pales next to the first film's brilliance,
it still deserves a recommendation.
it is a film that lets you enjoy a pleasant time
right there in the cinema.
smooth pacing, tight jokes,
and tech that soars beyond limits—
you can glimps
se the golden-er
ra Disney in its spiri
given Disney's track record in recent years,
this film is already a stellar effort—what more
could you ask for?
so I recommend you watch 'Zootopia 2' in the cinemas.
the original 'Zootopia' was packed with metaphors,
using a simple fairy tale
to explore racial tensions within American society.
it also poked fun at many modern-day woes,
which earned the film tremendous praise from viewers.
This time Disney stuck to the series' style
and packed the film with many metaphors about U.S. society
but the US changed so swiftly over these past ten years
these metaphors felt like US-
-only Lovecraftian stuff—Chinese folks couldn't parse them,
and Americans wished they couldn't either.
Zootopia 1 also unpacks much of American society,
yet its surface tale is very universal —
a country girl moving to the city to chase her dreams.
when we see Judy's excitement as she enters the big city,
and her video calls with family in a noisy rental flat
seeing her flustered by her parents' nagging yet faking
that she's doing fine,
we can easily empathize with this plucky little bunny.
and the second film is just way too America-centric
big money rigging votes,
Native Americans evicted — I must clear my name,
patent wars, and even group-therapy chats —
all so very American.
this means Chinese viewers can grasp
what they're talking about,
yet feel no connection to the themes they explore.
just laugh at memes and Nick & Judy ship, nothing more to it
but if you see Zootopia through an American viewer's lens,
it feels like hell.
In Zootopia, elections are rigged,
and the mayor is just a pawn of the moneyed clans.
Mayor Winddancer, the city's official ruler,
is a golden retriever with a flair for the dramatic.
in the underworld, there's Big Boss,
a mob don who might toss you in the trunk
and kill you—snap his face,
and your camera gets smashed on the spot.
and this mob boss could still attend elite soirees
in a respectable guise.
The Lin Shixiang Family is a textbook deep state —
respected and reputable in public view
as top-tier entrepreneurs,
yet behind the scenes they summon the mayor to give orders.
back then folks just laughed off such claims as conspiracy,
but after Donald Trump and Sleepy Joe kept stirring the pot,
now many find it hard to deny such things exist
just pull out one of their younger sons,
and they could run a smuggling route
to ship catnip into town for human trafficking.
most creatures in the city
are stuck screwing bolts on assembly lines;
in the last film, Fox Nick, who roamed the streets,
was seen as Zootopia's underclass.
this one tells you straight:
there are slums at the city fringe
that the mainstream won't even glance at
these slums are set to be torn down due to city plans,
yet the locals have no say in the matter at all
just these themes—when American viewers see them,
they likely won't smile,
for while we talk of metaphors,
they are living the metaphor itself
America is indeed a salad—many ethnic groups
tossed together in one bowl
when wolves and sheep clash, we just think of Pleasant Goat
which grating neighbor they might think of is anyone's guess
and after laying out so many conflicts and issues
that American viewers could truly relate to,
the show's final solution is...
if everyone has a heart of tolerance
and accepts that others differ,
all will be fine
such folks. The theme of mental illness.
Chinese viewers find this easier to take.
because for years we've watched American films
that all push the same open-minded values
if you dare say it,
I'll believe—just treat it as a tale of light
but in today's US,
where the poor must borrow to buy lunch,
and churches hang up when asked for formula
in Seattle's icy nights,
telling Americans about openness and tolerance,
about embracing what's different—sounds
a bit smug and out of touch
this is like being dragged by four men deep into Amazon,
into a cave where no satellites reach
you frantically activate the life-saving tool
your dad left you,
then lights flash—four words appear in the sky
Believe in self—none stay unshaken?
because it's far, and we can't feel it firsthand,
we can instead enjoy more purely
the joyous bits in 'Zootopia 2'.
at best one might feel
this fell just a tad short of striking chords
but we still believe
that fairy tale world Disney painted for us truly exists.
but when Chinese viewers check if Fox and Bunny are OOC
what U.S. viewers see is the slums near their own homes
that have never been truly resolved —
the 'reptiles' slums.
they made their own tragedy,
while we saw it as a poorly received comedy by chance
If we dig deeper,
Zootopia 2 still holds many intriguing elements.
which real-world group the reptiles symbolize
is a topic many have debated fiercely.
The first guess is Native Americans,
since the film nods to 'The Shining,'
where beneath the hotel lay
where Native Americans were slaughtered.
and beneath Lin Shixiang Manor lies the reptiles' birthplace
drive Native Americans out and build estates on their land —
a very American move indeed
the second pick is Latino,
since reptiles have many Latin traits,
and their plight mirrors Mexican workers
amid U.S. immigration tensions
Many folks don't know
that the US didn't start with its current shape.
the American West,
all of California, was once Mexican territory
the US invaded Mexico and seized the whole West Coast,
thus becoming a superpower spanning two oceans.
Mexicans had to hide in jungles to survive;
now when they sneak back into the U.S.,
they're called dangerous
undocumented migrants and told to leave.
the snake clan's tale in the film
mirrors it—nine or ten parts alike, at least.
the second candidate is overly smug—he is Gary's ancestor
who laid the groundwork for Zootopia,
yet is now seen as a threat.
and Gary is voiced by ethnic Chinese,
which evokes Chinese laborers and the Pacific Railroad
the Chinese laborers built the lifeline
linking East and West for the US,
yet no Chinese faces appear in the Pacific Railroad
completion photos.
they laid the groundwork for America,
yet faced slurs and hostility;
they were herded into Chinatown,
subjected to the Chinese Exclusion Act,
and branded the Yellow Peril.
now, their kin are once more painted as foes of the world
if it weren't for Hollywood,
they'd likely ignore Chinese voices—
I'd vote for that scenario.
One image yields three archetypes—indeed,
America has inherited UK's proud legacy
of great virtue and flaws.
but I can see a fourth possibility
here—one far more perilous—do you recall
what led the main group
to Grandma Garry's old hometown?
a beacon, buried in snow,
the last glimmer of light that beacon held.
In 1991, George H. W. Bush gave a speech
declaring the United States to be the 'Lighthouse Nation.'
in Zootopia 2, the big capital clans buried this original land
and the beacon that once lit the world.
they hunted beacon's descendants,
used cash and spin to hide the truth,
and kept expanding their domains,
burying more free lands beneath the snow
Animals with territorial drives
can't resist the urge to expand—does this refer to lynxes
or capital?
the beacon in the film, with its last faint glow,
led its descendants home once more
Does the beacon in truth still cast that faint light?
So why is the reception of 'Zootopia 2' so polarized?
The divide lies not in the film itself,
but in the world beyond the screen.
We still watch plays, but they have long lived in the script.
Thanks for watching, I'm backlash —
a cheerful rogue who sees only subjectivity, no objectivity.
If you like my content,
please follow and hit the Triple Combo.
Thank you all!